MICHAEL W. KEARNEY, PH.D.

NLP/AI SCIENTIST

mike.wayne.kearney@gmail.com

(816) 447-8650

★ mikewk.com in mikewk
O mkearney kearneymw

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Internationally recognized expert in Data Science, Natural Language, and Artificial Intelligence with over seven years of professional experience, strong theoretical and quantitative backgrounds, and a knack for finding and implementing innovative solutions to complex problems.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

A.I. CONSULTANT

Aware (client)

Michael Kearney
AI Consulting LLC

2023

- Provided expertise and guidance related to the use and development of artificial intelligence
- Created user-friendly documentation and database-specific tips/tricks for working data scientists
- Evaluated and proposed improvements to model training and evaluation pipelines

SENIOR DATA SCIENTIST

BI Team & Data Labs

Aware

2021-2023

- Converted natural language model training pipelines from Airflow to Sagemaker
- Owned, refined, refreshed, etc., the two featured language models sentiment and toxic speech
- Enabled, trained, and extensively data mined for multilingual development of models
- Parameterized model training and added extensive feedback (metric logging)
- Refactored large language models in PyTorch, added configurability, and enabled GPUs
- Automated model evaluation with Sagemaker pipelines and added real-world robustness checks
- Authored model performance reports on inputs, parameters, and metrics (precision, recall, f1, accuracy)
- · Identified, mined, and built pipelines for collecting diverse external sources of data
- Created labeling rule books, documented examples, and trained/worked with third party annotators
- Provided public-facing and client-facing topic analysis of workplace collaboration messages
- Mentored junior team members and frequently created tutorials and added to documentation
- Created internal packaging for data visualization and sampling, aggregating, and uploading to S3
- Used SQL and Athena to efficiently work with customer data stored in DynamoDB, Athena, and Redshift
- Created and worked with datalakes, Apache Arrow columnar format, and unstructured JSON data

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

School of Journalism & Informatics Institute

University of Missouri

2017-2021

- Developed and taught courses on social media data, networks, machine learning, research methods, etc.
- Mentored over 50 masters' students and chaired dozens of journalism theses and data science captstones
- Chaired two doctoral dissertations on computational analysis of social media and data visualization
- Created, reviewed, and researched open-source AI bot detection software
- Developed and maintained popular open-source data science tools for working with digital trace data
- Served on various school and university committees related to data, education, and diversity

INSTRUCTOR/CONSULTANT

Communication & Research Methods Center

University of Kansas

2012-2017

- Provided analysis and guidance on interdisciplinary research projects across university system
- Contributed to project automating personalized analytics for students in a large school district
- Created rtweet, a massively popular and influential R package for collecting and analyzing Twitter data
- Instructor of record for courses on public speaking, research methods, and leadership
- Facilitated working groups on data science and machine learning topics

TOOLS

LANGUAGES
SERVICES
DEV-OPS
DEEP LEARNING
MACHINE LEARNING
NATURAL LANGUAGE
DATA SCIENCE
DATA VIZUALIZATION

Python | R | SQL | Git | Docker | Bash | JavaScript
AWS[s3,sagemaker,ecr,athena,redshift] | REST APIs
Azure | Jira | GitHub | Gitlab | Confluence | Trello
PyTorch | TensorFlow | HuggingFace | Keras
XGBoost | FastText | scikit-learn | tidymodels
Spacy | HuggingFace | nltk | RegEx | scikit-learn
polars | pandas | numpy | tidyverse | data.table
ggplot2 | ggvis | plotly | matplotlib | d3js

SKILLS

THEORY
PRACTICE
ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE
MODELING
UNSUPERVISED
TEAMWORK
LEADERSHIP

Communication | Media | Interpersonal | Opinion & Topic Mining
Human Annotation | Heuristic & Algorithmic Labeling | Sampling & Bias
LLMs | Transformers | RNN/CNN | GRU/LSTM | MLP
Regression | Multilevel| Panel | ANOVA | Structural Equation
Topic Modeling | Network Analysis | PCA/CFA | Similarity
Research Team | Experienced Multitasker | AGILE Project Philosophy
Project Management | Team Supervisor | Committee Member & Chair

EDUCATION

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (PH.D.)	University of Kansas	Lawrence, KS	2017
Communication & Social and Beha	vioral Sciences Methodology		
MASTER OF ARTS (M.A.)	University of Kansas	Lawrence, KS	2014
Communication			
BACHELOR OF SCIENCE (B.S.)	Missouri State University	Springfield, MO	2012
Socio-Political Communication			

PUBLICATIONS (SELECTED)

PEER-REVIEWED ARTICLES

- Comparative approaches to misinformation, Int. J. Commun.. 2021
- Exploring gender differences on Twitter with NLP, J. Lang. Soc. Psychol.. 2021
- Collecting and analyzing Twitter data, J. Open Source Softw.. 2019
- Analyzing change in network polarization. New Media Soc.. 2019
- Two tests of social displacement through social media use, Inf. Commun. Soc.. 2018
- Interpersonal goals and political uses of Facebook, Commun. Res. Rep.. 2017

POPULAR PRESS ARTICLES

- March Madness office talk on par with Vegas odds, PR Newswire. 2023
- Doubts cast over Elon Musk's Twitter bot claims, BBC News. 2022
- Using data science to uncover mystery author of Times' Op-ed, Rynl. Jrnl. Inst.. 2018
- Trusting News project report, Rynl. Jrnl. Inst.. 2017

OPEN SOURCE SOFTWARE

- rtweet: Collecting Twitter data. 1,100,000 downloads / 491 citations
- tweetbotornot2: Detecting Twitter bots. 100,000 downloads / 27 citations
- textfeatures: Extracts features from text. 43,000 downloads /4 citations